what about fats fat fatty acids good
fats bad fats necessary fat sourcing of
them fats and cholesterol and their
relationship to the brain you know it's
hard to again be judgmental on fats come
back to the to the good and bad you know
it just drives me crazy that people call
a good cholesterol and bad cholesterol
number one to call it cholesterol is is
a misnomer
I mean LDL and HDL they're lipoproteins
I mean they're significantly more than
just cholesterol but we've got them
classified as cholesterol the the LDL
though I mean people look at it as bad
cholesterol and it's a truly wonderful
cholesterol I mean it is like a
low-density lipoproteins LDL I mean they
transport fats all over our body for use
in really healthy functions right you
know there are different types of the
LDL and you can you can classify that on
a particle test which is important to do
but to classify LDL is all bad
cholesterol and all HDL is good is
really not accurate and and again you
know just get rid of the judgment on
that and understand what you're looking
at more so those who don't know like
what does LDL do that's useful you
mentioned transport fats but I don't
think most people know the role that it
has in say hormones steroid hormone
pathways or what the brain is made up of
ER I mean cholesterol is that is a core
and LDLs transport cholesterol as well
so they're taking cholesterol around I
mean our brain has a ton of cholesterol
in it or every cell wall in our body is
made up of fats and cholesterol and this
LDL is transporting stuff around
delivering it our hormones are hormones
like the core component of hormones that
they're produced from is cholesterol
vitamin D is made from cholesterol so
we've got all of these really beneficial
aspects of cholesterol and yet we put
people on these low cholesterol diets
which are basically killing them
because there you're limiting an
essential thriving type of nutrient that
that shouldn't be classified that way
you know these these fats and and there
are there are good and bad but most of
the time the good and bad are related
more so to your individual genetics and
and how your body responds to it I mean
you look at the French and Mediterranean
paradox and they consume significantly
more fat I mean the Mediterraneans alone
consumed 40 to 50 percent of their
calories in fat and have the lowest
heart disease rate well why is that well
one genetics and two they consume the
majority of their cholesterol in the
forms of olive oil or fats in the form
of olive oil I mean almost 50 percent of
their calories they drink almost a liter
a week of olive oil on a classic
Mediterranean dietary pattern I mean a
liter a week of olive oil I try to get
that I think it's a highly beneficial
from an epigenetic standpoint I mean
these things impact not only the direct
utilization of these fats in creation of
of hormones and and other lipoproteins
throughout the body but they also alter
epigenetic expression so they can change
gene expression omega-3s and olive oil
both monounsaturated fats and omega-3s
they are wonderful about how they change
gene expression in a very positive way
in people now omega sixes and saturated
fats they can be good for some people
but they can also be significantly
problematic in people it just depends on
the individual now a mega threes and and
and monounsaturated fats typically
pretty good across the board but not the
omega sixes and the saturated fats and
so that's why it's important to
understand your body's response to those
because they can have a profound
difference in the body's body's outcome
with the intake of those kind of
nutrients and you know everybody groups
fat into one macronutrient and we don't
I mean it should never have been
if I'd that way I mean you've got to
look at fats as separate macronutrients
you have saturated fat you have Omega 9
omega-6 and omega-3 s and and look at
them from that macronutrient standpoint
rather than looking at them as fats as a
general recommendation okay so I'm going
to ask you a bunch of questions and
they're so ok you you mentioned a pretty
high amount of olive oil intake and so I
imagine that's going to be an actionable
step some people follow up with it's all
olive oil created equal
no no there's a I don't have to often
send you the link that you can put in
the podcast but there's a really good
evaluation of olive oils and in the
United States
apparently the rule is that you can
still call it extra-virgin olive oil and
still add certain amounts of vegetable
oil to it and it also happens in a lot
of the European olive oils that are
shipped into the United States
so you've got to get it number one from
a very reputable source and you want to
make sure that that you're getting it in
a dark bottle you know people people are
afraid to cook with extra virgin olive
oil because of the smoke point but I've
spent some time in Italy with some
dietitians in Italy and looked at the
studies on cooking with extra-virgin
olive oil and unless you're deep-frying
with it and using it over several days
in the deep fryer you're not going to
really get the R in Sidda T to it that
can create problems with the oxidation
of the olive oil so your the oxidation
of the fats in the olive oil so you're
still pretty good to go ahead and
stir-fry with it your you can cook on
higher heat with it without the risk of
significant problems so I think this is
a point that maybe not everyone knows in
terms of saying bad fats there are
certain kinds of fats that I think
everyone really wants to avoid trans
fats definitely and oxidized fats yeah
you want to describe those categories
and be a little bit yeah I mean the
trans fats is it's a it's a fact that
the body is incapable of utilizing in
any way it's like a foreign material to
the body I mean you want to talk about
synthetic that is truly synthetic
and the body is incapable of in any way
using it and it gets stored in the body
and unfortunately you know it's just
like any of the organic toxins that we
have I mean we store those in them in
the fat cells in our body but trans fats
are very similar they get stored in for
years we used Crisco which was just pure
trans fat paste that we used in
everything before we realized that it
was really creating all the health
problems that that are happening but you
know when when fats get oxidized and and
what happens is a double bond within the
fat itself will get hit with a free
radical and that free radical will add
an oxygen to that double bond and that
creates what we call a rancid fat or an
oxidized fat and those are ones that the
body recognizes and says oh this is this
is foreign material this is bad this is
an invader I've got to wall it off and
they're the ones that get put into the
walls of the vessels and particularly
rancid fats are the ones that have a
higher carcinogenic load yes so the
people understand that trans fat
basically means I hate hydrogenated fat
some kind of unsaturated fat they had
hydrogen added so this is your margarine
Crisco vegetable shortening when you
take anything that says partially
hydrogenated soybean oil all of that
should be kind of rigorously avoided and
you I don't think you can eat fast food
and avoid it so that's a good point and
so fat that is damaged by hydrogenation
should be avoided oxidized so this
typically happens when you're cooking
particularly sensitive fats at too high
a temperature and so you notice there
are some fats that are so sensitive like
fish oil or flax oil that you keep in
the fridge all the time because they can
oxidize even at room temperature over a
long enough period so many people like
to if they're going to have their fat in
touch with a pan right if they're gonna
have it at that heat just go straight to
a healthier saturated fat like coconut
oil or butter or palm oil what are your
thoughts on that well like I said I
I found that the studies on the
extra-virgin olive oil does not create a
significant amount of oxidation even
with the high heats and you know I used
to be the big proponent of you know
don't use extra virgin olive oil for
high heat cooking but then when the data
started coming out on it and I started
speaking with a lot of the the Italian
dietitians and we've looked at the data
the research data on what it takes to
truly oxidize the extra-virgin olive oil
I realized that it's not only the
temperature but the time and that is
something that I think a lot of people
miss is that they're they're looking at
you know oh it's the high heat well it's
the high heat plus the time of exposure
to that high heat that's important so a
fast stir-fry is gonna be different than
a long simmering process and I yes so I
would actually love to see that data if
you can send it to me and then I'll even
link it in this podcast if we can
because I still AM of the mindset that
cooks with coconut oil or a saturated
fat that has a much harder time
oxidizing because it's all double bonds
so I'd be interested to see that and
thank you so so we mentioned that
cholesterol is obviously necessary
there's also issues of oxidized
cholesterol yeah so how does that happen
well any fat can oxidize I mean it's
just free radicals I mean anytime you
have a double bond a double bond can get
oxidized by an oxygen free radical
because it's circulating around looking
for a place to really you know get a get
a donor electron there so it's looking
around for these these potential sites
and double bonds are the the clear
target and the the fats the double bonds
and the fats are easy pickins for these
free radicals and anytime something gets
oxidized I mean it's just not a natural
process anymore once that oxidation
occurs the body looks at it and says
okay there's something wrong with this
and I have to do something to react to
it so
any oxidation process is going to create
an inflammatory response it's going to
create some type of protective response
from the body so when you take
particularly sensitive fats and
cholesterol right some of the highly
polyunsaturated like that are in fish
and that are in good DHA free-range eggs
do you cook them differently factoring
that you know the biggest the biggest
thing to consider is the how much free
radical production a person typically
has I mean I think that's important to
consider when you're and this goes back
to looking at the whole picture of
things rather than you know going
straight to this and saying okay this is
a good or a bad thing
you look at the overall picture so why
do people get a negative response from
from a fad that's that's consumed that
could potentially oxidize well you know
you could eat really healthy fats that
and you and not consume oxidized fats or
trans fats but if you're generating a
lot of free radicals you're gonna create
your own inside your body anyway so what
you want to do is you want to mitigate
all the processes that are involved if
you can so you minimize the inflammation
you minimize the free radical production
as much as you can I don't think free
radical scavenging is the best way to go
in general because the body does a
pretty good job of controlling free
radicals and most people and the people
who would benefit most from free radical
scavengers are the really the couch
potatoes that are just not really
concerned about their health and they're
not going to take supplements to begin
with and the ones that are eating
healthy that are generally taking
supplements are the ones that typically
don't need the free radical scavengers
because you're not producing as many
free radicals from the from the
inflammation altogether to watch the
full episode or to subscribe to the
podcast click the link in the
description or
us at neuro hacker.com slash collective
insights
[Music]
you